We had made it to France.
Our flock had been following the Atlantic coast for weeks. Spring was blooming around us, the air was balmy, the fields green and filled with food.
We knew the end of our journey was near, so we made it last.
We were only travelling for a few hours a day, spending the rest of the time eating and resting on the shore.
And then one day, we saw it. England.
We had been flying for about an hour, when something strange appeared in the distance.
It looked like a city, but there was something eerie about it.
A world of green and grey, with hundreds of tiny human constructions made out of wood, plastic and fabric flapping in the wind. Almost like a ghost town.
There were no trees, so we decided to land on power lines encircling the place.
“What is this?” I asked Banjoko.
“They call it the Jungle” replied my friend. “The last stop before England. Can you see?”
He pointed at the horizon.
Behind the shadow of that strange city, beyond the ocean, I could spot it in the distance.
The silhouette of a gigantic island, blurry in the morning mist, almost like a mirage. The end of our quest.
Then I heard some laughter coming from below. I felt a sharp, sudden pain on my back and all went black.
I woke up a few hours later to children’s voices.
“Do you think it’s alive?”
Three pairs of giant, shiny black eyes stared at me from above.
I tried to fly away, but thick iron bars violently hit me in the chest.
I panicked. I flapped my wings, desperately trying to find a way out, but everywhere I went a metal barrier stood between me and the world.
Then I heard the voice of Banjoko.
“Mawusi!” He never called me by my name, that’s how I knew how scared he was.
We were in a dark, covered place. There were dozens of us, a few sand martins, but also swallows, cuckoos, even one magpie.
Humans had locked us all in tiny wire boxes. I was alone in mine.
Suddenly, I heard a clicking sound and a huge hand entered my prison.
I closed my eyes in terror, then felt five thick fingers wrapping tightly around my body.
I couldn’t breathe, my heart was pounding in my chest, I thought it was the end, then all of a sudden, I saw the light.
The afternoon sun blinded me completely, a fresh gust of wind ruffled my feathers and it took me a few seconds to realise I was free.
There was no time to think, so I spread my wings, took off and flew to the top of a utility pole to pull myself together.
On the ground, a little human girl was looking at me. She waved.
“Humans. Disgusting creatures.”
I heard the disgruntled voice of one of our leaders perched on a power line next to me.
“We’d better hit the road”
“But…” I muttered “My friend Banjoko is still in that tent. Surely we can…”
“My daughter is in there too”, he interrupted me with a bitter voice.
“What do you want me to do about it? Risk the lives of the whole flock and lose more members?
That’s the tough law of migration, kid. Just consider yourself lucky and move on.”
I froze, my eyes filled with tears.
He added with a softer voice.
“It is your first time. I remember how hard it felt. But believe me, time will toughen you up.”
Then without another word, he took off, and the flock followed him.